(字幕製作:貝爾)
好,今天我們就會說
平安
Peace
如果我們用一個字去describe 2022
你會用什麼字呢?
Describe 2022
Everybody shout out their word, okay?
Shout out with their word
你會用什麼字呢?
Stuck
Stuck, okay,還有呢?
What word would you use?
VAR
Okay
世界盃VAR, okay
(笑)
我會用一個字
就是Uncertainty
Uncertainty, okay
為什麼呢?因為我們還有
一個Virus
Coronavirus, 是不是?
上年Omicron
was the height of Omicron
我那時就在
在多倫多
在Omicron那時,多倫多
Okay, and then
We had all these lockdowns, right?
We had all these lockdowns
有沒有人lockdown過的?
在香港,有沒有人?
Do you remember?
你不知道喔,可能你的building
有幾個case,他就lockdown
你的building
然後又要test,又要
isolate幾天, okay
So it was a tough time
of isolation
of Coronavirus, it was not
fun, it was not fun
還有什麼發生?
2月那時有什麼發生?
有什麼發生,記不記得?
有什麼發生?
Big event
in February, 有什麼發生?
記不記得?
Why? Chinese New Year?
不是日語,不是這樣
Chinese
Okay, another big event that happened was
Ukraine being attacked
by
I can pretend I didn't hear that
being attacked by Russia
and that changed a lot of things
that were happening in the world
a lot of things that were happening
in the world
And we saw thousands of refugees
being displaced all over Europe
And that led to the threat of a nuclear war
There's like a threat of a nuclear war
It's serious, right?
Russia, US
They have the most nuclear weapons
in the world
And with that comes the rise of energy prices
Energy prices
And the stock markets went crazy
The markets went crazy
Housing has gone down
There's a lot of uncertainty
In the world
And something also very bad happened
Someone very famous died
What was her name?
Queen Elizabeth
And she was reigning
For many, many years
And it was a shock
To have the queen die
It was not all sad
It's just a lot of bad events
There were some positive events
Travel started to happen
People started traveling again
Who's traveling soon?
Where are you going?
Barcelona?
Ok, don't get robbed
Where are you going?
Canada?
Japan
Who's going to Japan soon?
Everyone is going to Japan
Or is in Japan right now
Ok, what else happened?
What VAR event happened?
World Cup
Who thinks it was the best
World Cup finals ever?
Raise your hand
For those who didn't raise their hand
Do you know who's the messy fan?
Yeah, 8 billion people
That's a lot of people
A lot of people
So what I would say is that
2022 was a year of uncertainty
There's social and political uncertainty
There's still a lot of protests
around the world
There's a lot of political uncertainty around the world
There's economical and financial uncertainty
There's a threat of a recession
Financial difficulty happening
There's the global health uncertainty
We still don't know
How the virus is gonna end
If it will end
And there is the uncertainty of the environment
Global warming
And also in Jesus' time
There was also uncertainty
What kind of uncertainty?
What was the major power of that time?
It was the Roman Empire
And so they gave uncertainty to Israel
Because they were always a threat
And the disciples were thinking
Wow, Jesus is the Messiah
He's come to save us
But then he said he's leaving
他去哪了?
他說我去那裡
你來不了
為什麼來不了?
And he says this
He promises this to the disciples
in the midst of uncertainty
He says this
Peace I leave with you
My peace I give to you
Not as the world gives
Do I give to you
Let not your hearts be troubled
Neither let them be afraid
And so Jesus promises peace
平安
你覺得平安的定義是什麼?
What is your definition of peace?
和你旁邊那個
談談你覺得平安的定義是什麼?
說一下
Ok, what is your definition of peace?
Ok, 我們先問這些女生
Annie 那組
What is your definition of peace?
Mentor Annie 那組
什麼?
Sean 走了
Sean 走了就是有peace
Wow
Ok
Ok 你那組呢?
有什麼定義?
平安是什麼?
不知道 不知道平安是什麼
喝湯
Calm
Calm, ok
喝湯也可以是平安的
Ok 你們呢?
你那組呢?
平衡
平衡, ok, that's a good definition
平衡, ok, very good
Pierre 你們這些男生有沒有定義?
No conflict, ok, very good
誰是no conflict的?
有沒有人是no conflict的?
Ok, Winnie 你的女生呢?
Are they searching it up on their phone right now?
It looks like it
What is peace on Google, right?
是嗎?
What is your definition, girls?
這些女生,什麼定義?
我們看一下這些女生
讓她們說定義
哈哈哈
What is peace?
平安是什麼?
Quietness
哈哈哈
Ok
Ok, what about the boys?
Lucas 你們呢?
What is the definition of peace?
The absence of bullying?
哈哈哈
Ok
很多人呢
覺得平安是什麼?
是沒有conflict
是沒有trouble的
是嗎? The absence of conflict
The absence of trouble
是什麼? Relax
好像在這個沙灘
Relax, calm
沒有東西煩你,是舒服的
That is what we strive for
in terms of this world
and peace
But Jesus
He's not just saying peace
In the Old Testament
they would use shalom
Ok, shalom means peace
and they would usually greet each other
是嗎?
你跟人家say hello
Hello, bye bye
在猶太人呢
就會說shalom, peace
Peace be with you
你走的時候也是shalom, peace be with you
但耶穌呢
不只是說bye bye
不是只是say hello
or bye bye
他是說peace I leave with you
Peace I give to you
耶穌的平安是什麼?
It is from him
He's saying I give you peace
Jesus will give you peace
My peace I give to you
還有呢
這個平安不是世界的平安
This is peace that the world cannot give
世界的平安和耶穌的平安是不同的
It's different
It is different
We learn here that Jesus provides peace
It's personal
and it is prized
I have this saying here
Peace does not come from your situation
but from your foundation
Peace doesn't come from your situation
It comes from your foundation
What does that mean?
We're going to look at four things today
The four things are
The cause of peace
The call to make peace
The challenge of seeking peace
in tough times
and the consequence of peace
What is the cause of peace?
The cause of peace comes from the Lord
一個神的名字是
The Lord of Peace
In Judges 6:24
Gideon calls him the Lord of Peace
耶穌的一個名字是
The Prince of Peace
For to us a child is born
To us a son is given
His name is Wonderful Counselor
Mighty God, Everlasting Father
The Prince of Peace
耶穌的名字是
平安在哪裏來的?
真正的平安在天府
在耶穌那裏
耶穌說
保羅說
The fruit of the Spirit is love, joy, and peace
Peace comes from the Holy Spirit
It is a product of relying on the Holy Spirit
Peace comes from the Lord
and is given by the Lord
He is the cause for peace
我記得我有一次
去菲律賓
誰去過菲律賓?
Anybody been to the Philippines?
Nobody? Just one person?
Two people?
So we were on a mission trip
This was our mission trip
As you see in the next slide
We were on a mission trip
And we went as a group
And we had to transit
In Manila
Who's been to Manila?
You guys don't like the Philippines?
Central?
Ok
So we had to transport
a transit in the Philippines
And what happened was
You had to go through customs once again
We lined up
to customs
We were in a group
We had 7 people in our team
And a guy said
Oh no
What do you think happened?
He left his passport
On the plane
Has anyone left their passport on the plane?
Rita?
Wow
Passport
Where did you leave it?
Vancouver
Wow
So where did this guy
Leave his passport?
In the front seat
Rita, you too?
Wow
He left his passport
Next time
When you fly
Put your passport in your wallet
Or in your bag
Don't put it in the front
Big mistake
Oh no
We have one hour left
We have to fly
What should we do?
We were thinking
Our whole team
We were waiting for our passports
We were sitting in the
Lost and found office
Rita, did you sit in the lost and found office?
No?
Oh wow
We were sitting in the
Lost and found office
We were thinking
We have a flight, it's in an hour
Can you help us get our passports
In the front seat
We were waiting
20 minutes
Till our next flight
And then half an hour to our next flight
And then 20 minutes
Oh no, he comes
We immediately got our passports
And went to customs
Pass through customs
We ran to our flight
And we made it back in time
In that time
We could blame this guy
We could be very annoyed
But in that moment
I trusted that God was in control
It's okay
That he left his passport
We can just stay
Another couple days in Manila
We can just wait for it
At customs
Or we can wait for our next flight
It's okay
Because we know that the cause of peace
Peace comes from God
True peace comes from
Knowing God is control
It requires faith
Not only is Jesus the cause for faith
He calls us to make peace
Not only is Jesus the cause for peace
He says, "Blessed are the peacemakers
For they will be called the children of God"
Blessed are the peacemakers
For they will be called the children of God
Paul also says
Finally, brothers, aim for peace
Comfort one another
Agree with one another
Live in peace
And the love and peace of God
Will be with you
How do we make peace?
Jesus is the ultimate example of making peace
How did he make peace?
Let's read in Ephesians chapter 2
How Jesus made peace
我們一起讀
一起讀
Ready?
One, two, three
For he, Christ himself, is our peace
Who has made us both Jews and Gentiles one
And has broken down in his flesh
The dividing wall of hostility
By abolishing the law of commandments
Expressed in ordinances
That he might create in himself
One new man in place of two
So making peace
Jesus first made peace
是什麼關係沒有平安?
是我們和誰?
和神的關係沒有平安
為什麼?因為我們有
有罪
Because of sin
罪的緣故
我們和神沒有平安
所以神就要怎樣?
差遣耶穌去做平安
所以神就做了平安
透過傳送耶穌
平安是購買的
是個人的
是購買在了耶穌的身上
神和我們建立了關係
所以首先
神和我們建立了平安
不僅是神和我們建立了平安
他也和我們建立了平安
他和我們建立了平安
因為耶穌死了
我們不再是猶太人和猶太人
我們是耶穌的一體
之前猶太人覺得他們是保證人
他們有法律
他們有神的祝福
而猶太人沒有
我們是保證人
但是耶穌為我們死的時候
他連接了我們
猶太人和猶太人
現在我們是耶穌的一體
透過信仰
耶穌也叫我們和別人做平安
誰去過台灣?
台灣
你會看到在下一個圖片
有一次我們去台灣的行程
我們在說行程的主題
Mavis去日本
我剛才說了菲律賓
現在我們說台灣
去台灣
我們有三個群體
第一個群體是很活力的
去做事
去傳福音
去幫人
去和人聊天
約新人
有些是很正常的
很輕鬆
但還有一個群體是怎樣的?
覺得很累
經常遲到
我有一點點病
我晚上沒有睡覺
我五點好像填胸圈才睡
是嗎?
所以怎樣?
我們做短訊
一個群體
就會有什麼?
有衝突
是嗎?
一個群體經常準備好
一個群體經常遲到
一個群體就說很累
可不可以休息一下?
可不可以去玩?
是嗎?
所以我們要怎樣?
做和平
去解決這些衝突
去成為一個群體
是,做和平
神想我們和祂和其他人和平
最後會說什麼關係?
是和我們自己
神會教導那些祂愛的人
當祂教導我們
就不愉快
是嗎?
誰喜歡被父母罵?
說真的嗎?
為什麼他們罵我們?
你哥哥喜歡
我知道你哥哥喜歡
罵多一點好一點
誰喜歡被父母罵?
不喜歡的
為什麼他們罵我們?
因為他們為我們什麼?
為我們好
可能那一刻我們不相信是好的
是嗎?
但最後我們看到
OK,應該是好的
應該早點睡
應該是收拾我們的房間
應該是不要吃那麼多糖
是嗎?
但在這個過程中
被教導
是很難的
它說
因此,如果有任何人在耶穌身上
祂就是新的創造
老的已經過世
新的已經出現
當耶穌讓我們新
需要執行
需要這個過程
這個過程
我們要接受自己的弱點
軟弱
接受我們自己有不同的試探
挑釁
我們需要和自己和平
特別是在艱難的時刻
我們要找到和平
我們一起讀
John 16
一起讀
1,2,3
我對你們說了這些話
在我身上你們可能有和平
在世界上你們可能有懲罰
但請記住
我已經克服了世界
耶穌說什麼?
我們這個世界會有什麼?
懲罰
會有困難
會有不同的
可能是身體上的挑戰
可能我們有病
受傷了
可能我們有心理上的挑戰
可能是抑鬱
可能是心理上的挑戰
可能我們和人的關係有挑戰
可能是世界有不同的挑戰
但耶穌說
祂給我們和平
因為祂已經克服了世界
我記得有一次
在夏天的時候
我撐著艇
在香港有誰曾經開過海盜艇?
有,很棒
你們可以看到
海盜艇和海灘的這張圖片
我開海盜艇的時候
在一個營裡
我和小朋友一起開海盜艇的時候
他就有一個想法
這個想法是什麼呢?
我們反船
Pastor Johnny的船
反船
最後他們六七個
就反船了
我的電話是一個水證件
但這個水證件
吊在我的頸上
我就把它脫掉
因為海盜艇的時候
這個風就會很大
很煩
我就把它脫掉
他反船的時候
我的電話就
升了下去
我們在梅窩
有沒有人去過梅窩?
水清不清?
是最不清的
最不清的
OK?
是最濕的水
不知道有什麼水池
一反船
你掌握著空氣
你的海盜艇就被翻轉了
你只是想拿空氣
然後
我的電話不是在浮動
是在滲水
我就說糟糕了
電話沒了
然後波浪又很大
我們就開始浮來浮去
潛下去就看不到東西
又不知道潛到
電話的最初位置
不知道在哪裡
在這個情況下
可以怪責小朋友
為什麼小朋友翻我的海盜艇
可以怪責我自己
為什麼不馬上拿著我的電話
可以怪責神
神啊
為什麼我在這裡的營裡去侍奉
但是有這個情況發生
為什麼
我可以做很多事情
但我接受了這個情況
我接受了神有更好的計劃
祂不想我那週末
拿著電話
我把我的安慰
我的信任
交給了神
祂會照顧我
我每次的約會
我每次的擔憂
我會有安慰
後來有人付了我新的電話
哇
有人付了我新的電話
所以神給了我
神給了我
我不是說如果你丟掉電話
神會給你新的電話
然後有人會付錢給你
我不知道阿姨Winnie
或者阿姨Rita會不會付錢給你
她可能不會
但是我說
如果你相信神
總有一天
事情會變好
你會有安慰
讓我們來評論
神想我們和祂有安慰
這是一個上升的關係
神想我們和其他人有安慰
神想我們和自己有安慰
特別是在艱難的時刻
但是如果你和神的關係沒有安慰
這會影響你所有的關係
如果你和神的關係沒有真正的平安
你所有的關係都會受到影響
和平不是來自你的情況
而是來自你的基礎
你的基礎必須是神
我們如何能夠有安慰
在艱難的時刻
我們必須確保我們的基礎堅強
耶穌說
不要在沙上建造你的房子
建造在石頭上
因為如果建造在沙上
如果你看到最後一張照片
那是一個石頭上的房子
如果這個房子在沙上
會發生什麼事
在最後一刻會發生什麼事
這個房子會進入海洋
會進入海洋
耶穌告訴我們要建造我們的房子在石頭上
我們要找到我們的平安
在一個堅強的基礎上
我會邀請樂隊上台
我們要閉上眼睛
我們要想想
基礎是什麼
我們閉上眼睛
現在是你和神之間
基礎是什麼
你的平安基礎是什麼
是你的等級嗎
因為如果你的等級高了
你會有平安
如果你的等級低了
你不會有平安
你會有多少人喜歡你
或者追蹤你
在Instagram上
因為人們會來
人們會走
如果我們建立我們的基礎
我們的平安
在不堪一擊的事情上
我們永遠都會上下走
如果我們把平安放在永恆上
神永不變
祂愛我們
祂稱呼我們為和平的建築
祂就是我們的平安
我們就真的會有平安
我不知道你們在過什麼
我們在2022年結束後
開始新的一年
你們可能會有很多擔憂
可能會有考試
可能會有家庭關係
可能會有朋友關係
可能會有個人的苦難
可能會在找平安的時候
在找到平安的時候
我今天要挑戰你們
因為祂在乎你們
祂愛你們
祂愛你們這麼多
祂在你們身上死了
祂愛你們
祂想讓你們有平安
祂不想讓你們依賴自己或別人
祂想讓你們依賴祂
祂想讓你們有平安
你們會相信祂嗎?
將你的信念放在祂身上
讓祂成為你們的平安
是世界無法給予的平安
讓我們祈禱
神父
我們感謝禰
禰是我們的平安
禰是平安的源頭
平安的起源
禰叫我們和禰和其他人和自己
一起做平安
在我們的弱點
在我們面對困難的時刻
幫助我們,主
和我們一起
我們在名字的神父的名下祈禱
阿們